Great. So to move one step closer to building awesome apps like the ones you
submitted to the discussion forum, we're going to learn about how to build up
the Sunshine UI. We'll do a quick recap first to help remind you of the concepts
that you learned in lesson one. In order to build a UI in Android, we use views.
Views are rectangles on the screen, and we may or may not see the borders of
that rectangle. Essentially, a view handles drawing and event handling. And
all the basic widgets in Android extend from this base class. The Android design
guide has visual examples of these basic building blocks of apps. For example,
we have the basic text field, as well as editable text fields.
We can do auto complete on them, and it comes with text selection as well.
Where it pops up a contextual action bar, for you to copy and paste.
There are also buttons, and also a suggestion to use borderless buttons.
It also has spinners, where you can select from a drop down menu.
There's also checkboxes, radio buttons, on/off switches, and
they also have some progress bars. There's a ton more basic widgets here, and
also in the Java docs. Check those out. And even ones that aren't listed here,
so. You'll come across them as you need them.
Now, if you want to display multiple views together, you'll need a view group.
A view group is a container for children views. Here are a couple of
common view groups, which Dan introduced earlier. First, we have a frame layout.
A child that gets added will be default positioned in the top left corner of
the view group. If you add a second view here, it will overlap the first one. So
typically we only have one child per frame layout. Next we have a linear layout,
it's composed of children either in a horizontal row or in a vertical column.
We can also specify layout weight. Lay out weight allows us to
distribute the width or height of a parent across the children. For example,
this has weight one, and this has weight one then the width of the parent can be
split across them evenly. Then we have a relative layout where we can specify
that a view should be aligned to the parent's left, top, right or bottom edge.
We can also specify that one view should be relative to another view.
It isn't full if the space is nicely compared to a linear layout, but
there are pros and cons to each. There's a grid layout where the views fill
up cells in a grid. You can also have views that span multiple cells.
I also want to point out that a view group is a view.
So in our code when we refer to a list item layout as being a single view.
That just means the root view of the whole view hierarchy for that layout.
Chances are that root view is a ViewGroup, so it contains children views as well
as ViewGroups. So basically you can nest ViewGroups within ViewGroups.
The reason why we care so much about parent child view relationships,
is because the way a child view gets laid out depends on its parent.
The simplest example of this is specifying a view's width and
height. By now you've seen that every view requires a height and
width. The two possible values are either wrap content or match parent.
This diagram shows all the possible combinations for width and height for
this text view. This is the balance of the view when we set wrap_content for
height and width. This is what happens when we do match_parent for
the width and match_parent for the height. And this is what happens when
both are set as match_parent. It shows the full dimensions of the parent.
When you run this on the device. All of these would visually look the same,
because you wouldn't see these boundaries. So why does it matter which one
we pick? Well, it matters as soon as you have other children that need to
be beside this view. And another reason is you want to specify gravity.
Let me spend a quick moment explaining gravity. Say for example, you
have this text view within a frame layout. By default, the text is left aligned.
And in this case, no gravity is set. If we specify gravity equals center,
then it will center the content within the text view. Vertically it can't move,
'because it's already centered, but horizontally it does shift over to be in
the middle. Instead of this. If we specify layout gravity equals center,
that means to center horizontally and vertically within the parent.
So we grab the whole child text view and we move it into the center.
Now it can't be centered horizontally, because it already takes up the max width
of the parent. If we really want to move the content to the middle,
then we should specify wrap content on this text view, so that it can be
moved to the center with this attribute. You can also specify padding and
margin on views. For example, if you added padding on this text view,
then it would shift the content inside by x amount on all sides.
If you specify layout margin to be x, then remember that the parent is
the one who will be interpreting this layout ground. In this case,
it adds a margin of x all around the text view. The text view is only this size.
When you render both of these, they would visually look the same.
Here's one case where it could matter. If this was a button and
you pressed it, there could be a gray background here showing. In some cases you
may want padding or margin or both. All views have a visibility property. For
this image view, it can be visible, invisible, or gone.
If it's invisible then it's not shown, but there's still a place holder for
it, we still have to go and measure the size of it. If it's gone,
then it's not even in the layout. It's as if it didn't exist in the XML.
You can also toggle the visibility of a view dynamically during runtime.
In the java doc, you can find all the possible XML attributes for that class.
It also shows inherited XML attributes, for example, from the view class.
For this image view, and then it shows the corresponding Java methods for
those attributes. Now as a briefer for [UNKNOWN] basics to help us get started,
but definitely check out the developer site for
more details later. Much like the real world, if you were working with a team to
build an Android app, you would start by implementing the wire frames first.
This has a correct flow for how the user will interact with the app. But
it doesn't have the final visual look and feel yet. We'll build this up step by
step, starting with the main activity then we'll move on to the detail activity
and then later build up the tablet UI. Then we'll receive a set of visual marks
red lines and assets, all of this will help us build a pixel perfect layout